We look around the media, as we see on the news from Iraq,
ننظر حولنا في وسائل الإعلام، فنرى الأخبار من العراق
Afghanistan, Sierra Leone,
أفغانستان، سيراليون
and the conflict seems incomprehensible to us.
و الصراع يبدو صعب الفهم
And that's certainly how it seemed to me when I started this project.
و الأكيد، تلك هي الصورة التي بدت لي عندما بدأت هذا المشروع
But as a physicist,
لكن، كفيزيائي
I thought, well if you give me some data,
فكرت، وقلت: لو تعطيني بعض البيانات
I could maybe understand this. You know, give us a go.
قد أتمكن من فهم ما يجري، أو على الأقل، أحاول
So as a naive New Zealander
و كنيوزيلندي ساذج
I thought, well I'll go to the Pentagon.
فكرت، لتكن وجهتنا الأولى البنتاغون
Can you get me some information?
هل يمكن تزويدنا ببعض المعلومات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
No. So I had to think a little harder.
غير ممكن. فكان علي التفكير أكثر
And I was watching the news one night in Oxford.
وفي إحدى اليالي كنت أتابع الأخبار في أكسفورد
And I looked down at the chattering heads on my channel of choice.
و نظرت إلى شريط الأخبار في قناتي المفضلة
And I saw that there was information there.
و رأيت أن المعلومات موجودة هناك
There was data within the streams of news that we consume.
البيانات موجودة في الكم الهائل من الأخبار التي نستهلكها يوميا
All this noise around us actually has information.
كل الضوضاء التي حولنا في الحقيقة تحمل الكثير من المعلومات
So what I started thinking was,
فاتجه تفكيري نحو
perhaps there is something like open source intelligence here.
لعل هناك جهاز مخابارات ذا مصدر مفتوح
If we can get enough of these streams of information together,
لو تمكنا من جمع العديد من هذه المصادر معا
we can perhaps start to understand the war.
فقد نتمكن من فهم الحرب
So this is exactly what I did. We started bringing a team together,
و هذا تماما ما فعلته، بدأنا بوضع فريق للعمل معا
an interdisciplinary team of scientists,
فريق من العلماء من مختلف التخصصات
of economists, mathematicians.
اقتصاديون و علماء رياضيات
We brought these guys together and we started to try and solve this.
جمعناهم، وبدأنا محاولة فهم ما يجري
We did it in three steps.
إتبعنا ثلاث خطوات
The first step we did was to collect. We did 130 different sources of information --
الخطوة الأولى هي الجمع. جمعنا 130 مصدرا مختلفا للمعلومات
from NGO reports to newspapers and cable news.
من تقارير المنظمات غير الحكومية، الصحف، والقنوات الفضائية
We brought this raw data in and we filtered it.
حصلنا على المعلومات، وقمنا بتصفيتها
We extracted the key bits on information to build the database.
استخلصنا أهم المعلومات لبناء قاعدة بيانات
That database contained
تحتوي قاعدة المعلومات هذه على
the timing of attacks,
توقيت الهجمات
the location, the size and the weapons used.
مكانها، حجم الأسلحة المستعملة
It's all in the streams of information we consume daily,
كلها موجودة في سيل الأخبار التي نسمعها يوميا
we just have to know how to pull it out.
وما علينا سوى معرفة كيفية استخراجها
And once we had this we could start doing some cool stuff.
فإذا حصلنا عليها يمكننا القيام بأشياء مبهرة
What if we were to look at the distribution of the sizes of attacks?
ماذا لو نظرنا لتوزع أحجام الهجمات؟
What would that tell us?
ماذا يمكن أن تخبرنا؟
So we started doing this. And you can see here
فبدانا القيام بذلك. و كما يمكن أن تروا هنا
on the horizontal axis
على المحور الأفقي
you've got the number of people killed in an attack
لدينا عدد الناس الذين قتلوا في الهجوم
or the size of the attack.
أو حجم الهجوم
And on the vertical axis you've got the number of attacks.
و في المحور العمودي لدينا عدد الهجمات
So we plot data for sample on this.
و نرسم البيانات على هذا المعلم
You see some sort of random distribution --
فنرى نوعا من التوزع العشوائي
perhaps 67 attacks, one person was killed,
ربما 67 هجوما، و شخص واحد يُقتل
or 47 attacks where seven people were killed.
أو 47 هجوما أين قتل سبعة أشخاص
We did this exact same thing for Iraq.
قمنا بنفس الشيء بالنسبة للعراق
And we didn't know, for Iraq what we were going to find.
ولم ندر ما سنجد في العراق
It turns out what we found was pretty surprising.
وما وجدناه كان مفاجئا جدا
You take all of the conflict,
خذ كل الصراع
all of the chaos, all of the noise,
كل الفوضى، كل الضوضاء
and out of that
و من كل ذلك
comes this precise mathematical distribution
يخرج هذا التوزع الرياضي الدقيق
of the way attacks are ordered in this conflict.
لطريقة تنظم الهجمات في هذا الصراع
This blew our mind.
هذه النتيجة حيرت عقولنا
Why should a conflict like Iraq have this
كيف يمكن لصراع كحرب العراق
as its fundamental signature?
أن يكون له توقيع أساسي كهذا؟
Why should there be order in war?
لماذا يكون هناك نظام و قانون في الحرب
We didn't really understand that.
لم نفهم ذلك
We thought maybe there is something special about Iraq.
اعتقدنا أن هناك شيئا خاصا بالعراق
So we looked at a few more conflicts.
فنظرنا إلى صراعات و حروب أخرى
We looked at Colombia, we looked at Afghanistan,
نظرنا لكولومبيا، أفغانستان
and we looked at Senegal.
و كذلك السنغال
And the same pattern emerged in each conflict.
و نفس النسق موجود في كل صراع
This wasn't supposed to happen.
هذا يُفرض ألا يقع
These are different wars, with different religious factions,
هذه حروب مختلفة، بعوامل دينية مختلفة
different political factions, and different socioeconomic problems.
عوامل سياسية مختلفة، و مشاكل اجتماعية و اقتصادية مختلفة
And yet the fundamental patterns underlying them
رغم كل هذا، النسق الأساسي المنظم لها
are the same.
نسق واحد
So we went a little wider.
ثم أردنا التوجه أبعد من ذلك
We looked around the world at all the data we could get our hands on.
نظرنا حول العالم لكل البيانات التي يمكن أن تصلها أيدينا
From Peru to Indonesia,
من البيرو لأندونيسيا
we studied this same pattern again.
درسنا هذا النسق مجددا
And we found that not only
ووجدنا أنه ليس مجرد
were the distributions these straight lines,
توزعا على خط مستقيم
but the slope of these lines, they clustered around
بل كذلك ميل هذه الخطوط، كلها مجتمعة حول
this value of alpha equals 2.5.
هذه القيمة لألفا تساوي 2.5
And we could generate an equation
و بإمكاننا استخلاص معادلة
that could predict the likelihood of an attack.
بإمكانها توقع احتمال وقوع هجوم
What we're saying here
بمعنى آخر
is the probability of an attack killing X number of people
احتمال أن يقتل هجوم ما عددا X من الأشخاص
in a country like Iraq
في بلد مثل العراق
is equal to a constant, times the size of that attack,
يساوي ثابتا، ضرب حجم هذا الهجوم
raised to the power of negative alpha.
أس ناقص ألفا
And negative alpha is the slope of that line I showed you before.
و ناقص ألفا هو ميل الخط الذي عرضته سابقا
So what?
ثم ماذا؟
This is data, statistics. What does it tell us about these conflicts?
هذه بيانات، إحصائيات، ليس إلا. ماذا تخبرنا عن الصراع؟
That was a challenge we had to face as physicists.
هذا هو التحدي الذي واجهناه كفيزيائيين
How do we explain this?
كيف يمكننا تفسيير هذا؟
And what we really found was that alpha,
وما وجدناه هو أن ألفا
if we think about it, is the organizational
لو فكرنا جيدا، هي الهيكل التنظيمي
structure of the insurgency.
الهيكل التنضيمي للحركات المتمردة
Alpha is the distribution of the sizes of attacks,
ألفا تعبر عن توزع أحجام الهجمات
which is really the distribution
الذي هو في الحقيقة توزع
of the group strength carrying out the attacks.
قوات الجماعة التي تنفذ الهجمات
So we look at a process of group dynamics:
لننظرلنظام ديناميكة المجموعات
coalescence and fragmentation,
التآلف و التجزؤ
groups coming together, groups breaking apart.
المجموعات حال تشكلها، و حال تجزئها
And we start running the numbers on this. Can we simulate it?
ثم يأتي دور الأرقام، هل يمكننا محاكاة هذا النظام؟
Can we create the kind of patterns that we're seeing
هل يمكننا خلق هذه الأنساق التي نشاهدها؟
in places like Iraq?
في أماكن كالعراق؟
Turns out we kind of do a reasonable job.
و على ما يبدو بإمكاننا القيام بعمل مقبول
We can run these simulations.
نستطيع إجراء المحاكاة
We can recreate this using a process of group dynamics
يمكننا محاكاتها باستعمال نظام محاكاة المجموعات
to explain the patterns that we see
لفهم النسق الذي نشاهده
all around the conflicts around the world.
في كل الصراعات حول العالم
So what's going on?
إذن، ماذا يجري هنا؟
Why should these different -- seemingly different conflicts
لماذا نرى، هذه الصراعات المختلفة ظاهريا
have the same patterns?
محكومة بنفس النسق؟
Now what I believe is going on is that
الآن أعتقد أن ما يجري هو أن
the insurgent forces, they evolve over time. They adapt.
القوات المتمردة تتطور عبر الزمن، و تتكيف
And it turns out there is only one solution
و على ما يبدو هناك حل وحيد
to fight a much stronger enemy.
لقتال عدو أقوى بكثير
And if you don't find that solution as an insurgent force,
إذا لم تجد هذا الحل كمجموعة مقاتلة
you don't exist.
فأنت غير موجود
So every insurgent force that is ongoing,
لهذا، كل قوات مقاتلة
every conflict that is ongoing,
وكل صراع موجود
it's going to look something like this.
سيظهر لنا بهذا الشكل
And that is what we think is happening.
و هذا ما نعتقد أنه حاصل هنا
Taking it forward, how do we change it?
لو تعمقنا أكثر، كيف يمكننا تغييرها؟
How do we end a war like Iraq?
كيف يمكننا إنهاء حرب كحرب العراق
What does it look like?
كيف تبدو لنا
Alpha is the structure. It's got a stable state at 2.5.
ألفا تمثل الهيكل، في حالتها المستقرة تأخذ قيمة 2.5
This is what wars look like when they continue.
هكذا تبدو الحروب عندما تستمر
We've got to change that.
علينا تغيير ذلك
We can push it up:
يمكننا دفعها للأعلى
the forces become more fragmented;
القوة تصبح أكثر تجزؤا
there is more of them, but they are weaker.
يوجد عدد كبير منهم، لكنهم أضعف
Or we push it down:
أو دفعها للأسفل
they're more robust; there is less groups;
هم الأن أكثر صلابة، لكن عدد المجموعات قليل
but perhaps you can sit and talk to them.
ربما بالإمكان الجلوس معهم و محاورتهم
So this graph here, I'm going to show you now.
إذن هذا المخطط هنا، الذي سأعرضه الأن
No one has seen this before. This is literally
لم ير هذا أحد من قبل، و هو في الحقيقة
stuff that we've come through last week.
نتائج حصلنا عليها الأسبوع الماضي
And we see the evolution of Alpha through time.
ونرى تطور قيم ألفا عبر الزمن
We see it start. And we see it grow up to the stable state
نراها تبدأ، تتزايد نحو الحالة المستقرة
the wars around the world look like.
التي تمثل الحروب حول العالم
And it stays there through the invasion of Fallujah
وتبقى على حالها خلال احتلال الفلوجة
until the Samarra bombings in the
حتى تفجيرات سامراء
Iraqi elections of '06.
في الانتخابات العراقية سنة 2006
And the system gets perturbed. It moves upwards
فيضطرب النظام، ونتحرك نحو الأعلى
to a fragmented state.
نحو حالة التشرذم
This is when the surge happens.
هنا عندما تقع العملية
And depending on who you ask,
و تبعا لمن تسأل
the surge was supposed to push it up even further.
العملية كان من المفروض أن تدفعها نحو الأعلى أكثر
The opposite happened.
لكن العكس يقع
The groups became stronger.
الجماعات تزداد قوة
They became more robust.
و تصير أكثر صلابة
And so I'm thinking, right, great, it's going to keep going down.
ثم أفكر لبرهة، حسنا، هذا عظيم، ستنخفض أكثر
We can talk to them. We can get a solution. The opposite happened.
يمكننا الأن الحديث إليهم، ربما نصل إلى حل، لكن العكس يقع
It's moved up again. The groups are more fragmented.
تتحرك نحو الأعلى مجددا، و المجموعات الأن متفرقة
And this tells me one of two things.
و هذا يخبرنا شيئا من اثنين
Either we're back where we started
إما أننا عدنا من حيث بدأنا
and the surge has had no effect;
و العملية العسكرية لم يكن لها فائدة
or finally the groups have been fragmented to the extent
أو أن الجماعات تجزأت لدرجة
that we can start to think about maybe moving out.
أننا يمكن الأن أن نفكر في سحب القوات
I don't know what the answer is to that.
أنا لا أعلم ما هي الإجابة
But I know that we should be looking at the structure of the insurgency
لكني أعلم أنه يجب علينا دراسة هيكلية الجماعات
to answer that question.
حتى نجيب على هذا السؤال
Thank you.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)